<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>

<info>
<title>Willkommen</title>

<author title="Author"><mail link="sebastian@werner-productions.de">Sebastian Werner</mail></author>

<date>18. Oktober 2002</date>

<box>
  <block>
    <title>Aktuelles:</title>
    <p>
      Was gibt es aktuelles bei Gentoo Linux. Hier erfahren Sie es...
    </p>
  </block>

</box>

<chapter>
<title>Aktuelles</title>

<section>

<title>Planung des Usertreffens</title>

<body>
<p>
Nachdem sich nun alle in die Liste für das Usertreffen eingetragen haben, stellt sich
nun die Frage, wo dieses stattfinden soll. Zu diesem Zwecke haben phoen][x und cybersystem
eine interaktive Karte eingerichtet, auf der Ihr Euch eintragen könnt. Die Karte sollte
weitestgehend selbsterklärend sein. Ihr findet die Karte <uri link="http://cybersystem.iq-computing.de/gentoo">hier</uri>
</p>
</body>

</section>

<section>

<title>O'Reilly Artikel über Gentoo Linux 1.4</title>

<body>
<p>
A new article introducing Gentoo Linux written by Daniel Robbins is featured 
on O'Reilly Network's Web site today. In the article, a brief overview of some 
of the features of Gentoo Linux, Daniel expounds on what kinds of enhancements 
users can expect in the 1.4 final release: support for true 64-bit on the 
UltraSparc architecture, KDE 3.0.4, a gentoo-sources kernel with Andrea 
Archangeli's 3.5GB "user address space" patch and grsec, and of course the new 
Gentoo Reference Platform for fast binary installs.
</p>
</body>

</section>

<section>

<title>Neue UT 2003 LiveCD</title>

<body>
  <p>
A new release of our Unreal Tournament 2003 Gentoo LiveCD is now
available and includes quite a few enhancements. The Unreal Tournament
2003 Demo has been upgraded to the 1080c patchlevel, fixing numerous
quirks in the game itself. In addition, the UT2003 LiveCD now is now
optimized for modern systems, requiring a Pentium Classic or greater to
run and optimized for a P6-class instruction set like the Pentium II and
III (it was previously a relatively unoptimized i486+ CD.) The CD now
supports monitors with and without EDID functionality as well as wheel
mice. In addition, machines with 512MB or more of RAM can now cache the
entire UT2003 Demo to tmpfs (RAM) to dramatically enhance load-time
performance. Oh, and SoundBlaster PCI 512 cards will now be correctly
detected.
  </p>
</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</info>
