<?xml version="1.0" encoding="iso-8859-1"?>


<info>
<title>Präsentation</title>

<author title="Author"><mail link="sebastian@werner-productions.de">Sebastian Werner</mail></author>

<date>18. Oktober 2002</date>

<box>
  <block>
    <title>Aktuelles:</title>
    <p>
      Was gibt es aktuelles bei Gentoo Linux. Hier erfahren Sie es...
    </p>
  </block>

</box>

<chapter>
<title>Aktuelles</title>

<section>

<title>Gentoo Linux in a paragraph</title>

<body>
<p>
Gentoo Linux is a versatile and fast, completely free Linux distribution for x86, PowerPC, UltraSparc and Alpha systems
that's geared towards Linux power users. Unlike other distros, Gentoo Linux has an advanced package management system called
Portage. Portage is a true ports system in the tradition of BSD ports, but is Python-based and sports a number of advanced
features including dependencies, fine-grained package management, "fake" (OpenBSD-style) installs, path sandboxing, safe
unmerging, system profiles, virtual packages, config file management, and more.
</p>
</body>

</section>

<section>

<title>Gentoo Linux 1.4_rc1</title>

<body>
<p>
Gentoo Linux 1.4 features Linux 2.4.19+ and a modern GNU development environment (glibc-2.2.5, gcc 3.2, XFS, ReiserFS, ext3,
EVMS, LVM, ALSA, pcmcia-cs support, "vanilla" (stock) kernel compatibility for those who prefer unpatched kernels, Xfree86
4.2, OpenGL, KDE 3.0 and 3.1_beta and GNOME 2.0.2, tcp-wrappers, xinetd, iptables and Linux QoS tools, modern qmail (with
optional mysql and LDAP support), postfix and exim MTAs, GRUB boot loader (LILO also available if you need it), 2400+
up-to-date ebuild scripts of your favorite apps, an innovative dependency-based startup script design, and of course
Portage, a completely open design and a great developer and user community.
</p>
</body>

</section>

<section>

<title>More about Portage</title>

<body>
<p>
Portage allows you to set up Gentoo Linux the way you like it -- with the optimization settings that you want, and with
optional build-time functionality (like GNOME, KDE, mysql, ALSA, LDAP support, etc.) enabled or disabled as you desire. If
you don't want GNOME on your system, your apps won't have optional GNOME support enabled, and if you do, then they will.
That's why we prefer thinking of Gentoo Linux as a meta-distribution or Linux technology engine. You decide what kind of
system you want, and Portage will create it for you.
</p>

<p>
We maintain an official Gentoo Linux Portage tree that contains the most recent versions of our ebuild autobuild scripts. By
updating your Portage tree, you gain instant access to the latest and greatest Linux technologies and applications. Tell
Portage what ebuild you'd like to install, and Portage will auto-download, unpack, patch, configure, compile and install the
package. Thanks to Portage auto-dependency resolution, you can install KDE 3.0 or GNOME 2.0.2 by typing in a single command,
and the resultant installed binaries will be optimized and customized to your exact specifications.
</p>

<p>
If this kind of power and flexibility appeals to you, then we encourage you to try Gentoo Linux for yourself. You won't be
disappointed.
</p>

</body>

</section>

</chapter>

</info>
