<!-- The content of this document is licensed under the CC-BY-SA license -->
<!-- See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-sa/1.0 -->

<!-- $Header: /home/xubuntu/berlios_backup/github/tmp-cvs/gentoo-deutsch/Repository/www-source/daten/doku/handbook/hb-install-next.xml,v 1.1 2003/11/22 08:08:02 jay Exp $ -->

<!-- Original English CVS Version 1.6 -->
<sections>
<section>
<title>Dokumentation</title>
<subsection>
<body>

<p>
Gratulation! Sie haben jetzt ein funktionierende Gentoo System. Aber wie 
geht es nun weiter? Welche Möglichkeiten bieten sich? Gentoo bietet
seinen Nutzern viele Optionen und daher auch viele dokumentierte
(und weniger gut dokumentierte) Eigenschaften.
</p>

<p>
Sie sollten einen Blick in das <uri
link="/doc/de/portage-user.xml">Portage Benutzerleitfaden</uri> 
werfen, welches Ihnen zeigt, wie Sie Ihr System auf dem aktuellsten Stand
halten und neue Software installieren können. Möchten Sie wirklich alles über
Portage wissen (aber den Source-Code nicht durchackern müssen), 
empfiehlt Sich das <uri link="/doc/en/portage-manual.xml">Portage
Handbuch</uri> welches einen ausführliche Beschreibung der Internas
beinhaltet.
</p>

<!-- Translation stops here -->

<p>
If you want to know more about how USE interacts, read the <uri
link="/doc/en/use-howto.xml">USE Howto</uri> which introduces USE flags to you
and helps you decide what USE flags you need.
</p>

<p>
If you are interested in optimizing your system for desktop-use, or you want to
learn how to configure your system to be a full working desktop system, consult
our extensive <uri link="/doc/en/desktop.xml">Desktop Configuration Guide</uri>.
</p>

<p>
For a full listing of all our available documentation check out our <uri
link="/doc/en/index.xml">Documentation Resources</uri> page.
</p>

</body>
</subsection>
</section>
<section>
<title>Gentoo Online</title>
<body>

<p>
You are of course always welcome on our <uri
link="http://forums.gentoo.org">Gentoo Forums</uri> or on one of our many 
<uri link="/main/en/irc.xml">Gentoo IRC channels</uri>.
</p>

<p>
We also have several <uri 
link="/main/en/lists.xml">mailinglists</uri> open to all 
our users. Information on how to join is contained in that page.
</p>

<p>
We'll shut up now and let you enjoy your installation :)
</p>

</body>
</section>
</sections>
